☐ liding256@gmail.com

**♦** Mountain View, CA

♦ https://liding.info

# RESEARCH SUMMARY

My research focuses on open-ended learning, AI safety, and multimodal generative models, with an emphasis on exploratory and self-supervised optimization. I have developed methods to enhance safety and creativity of generative models through reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF), and to improve generalization and robustness of foundation models.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **University of Massachusetts Amherst**

Ph.D. in Computer Science

2020.9 - 2024.7

- Dissertation: "Optimization with intrinsic diversity: Towards generalizable, safe, and openended learning".
- Committee: Lee Spector (Chair), Scott Niekum, Subhransu Maji, Jeff Clune.

# **Massachusetts Institute of Technology**

*Graduate Study in EECS (non-degree)* 

2019.9 - 2020.1

# **University of Rochester**

M.S. in Computational Science

2016.6 - 2017.5

• Advisor: Chenliang Xu

### Work

### Google

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Machine Learning Engineer

2024.7 - present

- Conducted research to enhance the performance and robustness of multimodal LLMs, focusing on parameter-efficient fine-tuning (LoRA) and quantization-aware training (QAT).
- Designed and implemented hardware-accelerated GenAI agents, optimizing performance on edge devices for scalable and reliable deployment.

# **Massachusetts Institute of Technology**

Research Engineer

2017.9 - 2020.6

- Performed research in deep learning for spatiotemporal perception and led the development of the MIT DriveSeg dataset for autonomous driving scene segmentation.
- Developed a multitask learning framework for joint face landmark detection and cognitive state assessment, improving both performance and efficiency.

#### INTERNSHIP

#### Google

Research Intern

2023.6 - 2023.9

• Developed a JAX optimizer for efficient neural architecture search of foundation models through knowledge distillation and meta-learning.

#### **CarperAI**

Student Researcher

2023.2 - 2023.6

• Proposed novel techniques to enhance the creativity of generative models through learning from human feedback, leading to more diverse and open-ended model behavior.

#### Meta

Research Scientist Intern

2022.5 - 2022.8

 Developed model architectures and transfer learning methods to optimize vision transformers for AR/VR capabilities.

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS GOOGLE SCHOLAR

- R. Boldi, <u>L. Ding</u>, L. Spector, and S. Niekum, "Pareto-optimal learning from preferences with hidden context," *under review at ICLR*, to appear at NeurIPS: Pluralistic Alignment Workshop,, 2024
  - POPL learns Pareto-optimal policies or reward functions in RLHF, addressing diverse group preferences without needing group labels, and offering safe and fair alignment of agents and LLMs.
- L. Ding, J. Zhang, J. Clune, L. Spector, and J. Lehman, "Quality diversity through human feedback: Towards open-ended diversity-driven optimization," in *ICML*, 2024
  - QDHF learns diversity metrics from human feedback and optimizes the discovery of novel solutions, enhancing task-solving capabilities of RL agents and boosting creativity of generative models.
- L. Ding, E. Pantridge, and L. Spector, "Probabilistic lexicase selection," in GECCO, 2023
- <u>L. Ding</u>, M. Zoghi, G. Tennenholtz, and M. Karimzadehgan, "Ever evolving evaluator: Towards flexible and reliable meta-optimization for knowledge distillation," in *NeurIPS: RealML Workshop*, 2023
- <u>L. Ding</u>, J. Terwilliger, A. Parab, M. Wang, L. Fridman, B. Mehler, and B. Reimer, "CLERA: A unified model for joint cognitive load and eye region analysis in the wild," *ACM Trans. Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI)*, 2023
- <u>L. Ding</u> and L. Spector, "Optimizing neural networks with gradient lexicase selection," in *ICLR*, 2022
- L. Ding, J. Terwilliger, R. Sherony, B. Reimer, and L. Fridman, "Value of temporal dynamics information in driving scene segmentation," *IEEE Trans. Intelligent Vehicles (T-IV)*, 2021
- <u>L. Ding</u> and C. Xu, "Weakly-supervised action segmentation with iterative soft boundary assignment," in *CVPR*, 2018

Honors	AND
AWARDS	

Google Research Travel Scholarship, *Google*.

2023

SOAR (Supporting Open Access Research) Fund, *UMass Amherst*. 4th Place (among 150 teams, top 3%), *MIT Miniplaces Challenge*.

2023 2019

Graduate School Scholarship (\$30,000), *University of Rochester*.

2016 2015

Meritorious Winner (top 5%), COMAP's Mathematical Contest In Modeling.

TEACHING

• TA for MIT 6.S094: Deep Learning for Self-Driving Cars.

2018 - 2019

2010 - 2017

• TA for MIT 6.S099: Artificial General Intelligence.

2018

• Co-instructor (w/ Tom Bertalan) for MIT Robocar Workshop.

2018

**COMMUNITY** 

• Reviewer for ICLR, NeurIPS, JMLR, CVPR, ICCV, ECCV, etc.

2020 - present

• Ph.D. Admissions Committee (UMass Amherst CICS).

2024

# OPEN SOURCE

pyribs: an open-source library for diversity-driven optimization.

PROJECTS

• Contributed the demo and tutorial for the QDHF work.

mit-deep-learning: MIT Deep Learning open courses (10k+ stars).

• Main contributor for tutorials and coding assignments.

MIT AI Podcast: now the Lex Fridman Podcast, 4M+ subscribers on Youtube.

• Helped find candidates and prepare interview materials.

**SKILLS** 

Python, C++, JavaScript, PyTorch, JAX, Tensorflow, Git, LLM workflows (instruction-tuning, PEFT, RLHF).